well you and I have never spoken so I
don't know how much introduction both of
us need to do for each other but why
don't you go first and then you can ask
me anything you want to ask me right I
see well I my name's guy Singh stuck um
I am uh where'd you grow up I grew it
well I grew up in Chicago uh
specifically Hinsdale Illinois was where
I was born which is about a half an hour
west of Chicago in Peru until I was
about 12 I grew up in that area Downers
Grove Westmont in stale claritin Hills
that area is till I was 12 I moved
Arizona was there till I was about 23
and then I moved to the Bay Area to go
to the San Francisco Art Institute okay
over on chestnut chestnut street in
North Beach okay and I've been that's
how I get to the Bay Area okay okay
did you go to well did you do any
undergrad stuff before the Art Institute
or is that your first college uh let's
see
I actually out of high school I went
right to massage school in Tucson okay
unusual um and and then I was actually
gonna and then I moved back to I lived
in Prescott that's where I graduated
high school and then I I went to massage
school for a year and then I moved back
to Prescott and got my practice going to
then enroll into I was gonna enroll into
Prescott college at the time Prescott
College I said it's considered probably
would most liberal school in the
universe really yeah yeah they had a
bachelor's degree in in in you mean
psychology and I was gonna take that and
then I got sick and I had this whole
kind of epiphany about about actually I
just wanted to be an artist and and so
shortly after that I ID and a
disenrolled and I moved out to San
Francisco and about a year took me about
a year to get my feet on the ground here
and then I I started started art school
okay
was her was your family religious at all
growing up well I've come to understand
that I think it's impossible to not be
religious in fact it seems it seems that
the less formally religious you are like
the more religious you can actually turn
out to be I agree with that about a lot
no no actually I I think we are Lutheran
by denomination but I I had no I had no
upbringing in that however I feel the
more I learn about Luther I feel deep in
my bones very much like him really yeah
it just I don't even know that that much
about about him but just the temperament
and like the orientation and the
rebellion in the sense of like the sense
of like betrayal and all the stuff that
I understand a little bit I know about
about Luther I'm I'm in fact in fact the
Christopher talked about in in your
interview and I thought this was really
striking where he talked about that you
know he was raised he was raised
Catholic and that as he gets older he
realizes how deep Catholicism is and and
I think that that really kind of points
to in fact I texted John right after I
heard that I took like John and for
Vicki and I have been having these like
like long dialogues or texts something
we could talk about about this whole
thing about what the hell are we doing
here honey you can describe all this and
talk about it you know but it seems
something both old and new at the same
time but it anyways what I texted John
after that I was I was I was thinking
about that that was really a profound
insight I think that he that he
demonstrated in making it right because
it it points
that it points I would say to that he's
finding himself more of a Catholic then
he didn't even understand and it but as
he gets older it emerges he can see yeah
he got points to wear something like
religion exists right it's like very it
it it it exists on the primordial level
the pre reflective level and organizing
some perceptions right these things and
that's what I mean by that's right so
when I'm talking about like it's almost
impossible to not be religious if you
have a phenomenology right right how you
how you have the most simplest
perceptions yeah there are when you get
down to him you almost have to use
religious terms to may start to make
sense of them yeah yeah Peterson made
that as made that point numerous places
I had a conversation with Sevilla king
who has the Equality existence channel
and she made a similar point when she
she went into clinical work when she was
starting her work in psychology and a
lot of you know free clinical work is
often in poor neighborhoods and as Chris
are made the point he made in his book
dignity if you live in poor
neighborhoods you're you're out you
don't find atheists they're just they're
just few and far between and you know
that has a lot to do with the role of
religion and it is I deal with people
all the time who you know via the jordan
peterson thing they they went through a
period of estrangement with religion and
then somewhere in their 30s and 40s or
50s or 60s even i've baptized people in
their 70s that they you know it's they
discover it so deep inside themselves
and they're curious about its presence
when they discover it but then of course
with with all of the tools hopefully
that they have after years of maturity
they can begin to do some assessment and
evaluation and come to some
some mature engagement with it so that's
that's very and and even if as you said
in your case even if he didn't go to
church much even if your parents you
know perhaps went to church more in
their youth that got into them and it
seeped up through them to you even
without having to darken the door of a
church it just it's just just built into
us so deeply yeah in the yes in all of
our social practices and all of our
customs or manners are are kind of
embodied pre reflective sense of because
it is one of the things I really like
about Heidegger cause he really as is
this understanding of historicity right
the sense the sense that there's nothing
that the human being does that's like an
object that exists in an environment
that then makes decisions and axes like
all of that were already always in a
historical context you know just for
example that you're going like that and
that you have a bookshelf and that you
have a chair and the way that you sit in
that chair that's right if we were to
break down like the countless
conversations and the countless
interactions and the customs and like
the history of the most simple gesture
is saturated with the gravity of this
unfolding history to this deep
temporality and one of the things I
really appreciated a lot about what you
say often is you often I don't know if
you say this person's what I hear is uh
is you talk about yeah we like to think
we like to we like to think that we're
very transparent to ourselves
you usually smirk or easily we like to
think that yeah you giggle like that you
know because it's it's it's actually
what part of being a human is is a big
part of it is that we're not yeah right
is that is that we kind of emerge we
find ourselves here already here
already begun and week I just remember
at some point when I was a kid these
faint little memories of these faint
little memories of just having this
sense of being on a playground and I'm
running down the field
I don't know I'm four or something or
five and just having these Inklings of
wait a minute I'm here and I'm all like
I'm already running and I have a first
and last name and a boatload of concerns
and I'm I kind of come to already begun
yeah yeah and that all that thing that
we emerge from right seems to be that it
seems to be like something about that
primordial Ness what I've understood in
my in in in now studying is right now
I'm starting a lot of st. Maximus the
Confessor okay
[Music]
and just because the rich because I've
some of the richness of what they're
actually describing is something like
that that that which were already
embedded in that when we then come back
and reflect upon that we come back and
try to make sense of that right first of
all the way that we make sense of it
matters right but also this kind of also
this sense
another thing that Christopher really
said and I've been thinking about it
ever since read where he talked about
you know were he's very present to that
we are in we are in the light of the
dying of a dying star of Christianity
yeah when he said that yeah it tickled
something it like a feeling in me that
was so difficult I didn't even have
quite words for but it brought it to the
center in that like because we don't
have for 2,000 years right it's we've
had this centralized coming together
that's been our conscious
representations right open
are our social practices and in the
primordial tea but now that's like like
fading away on some respects and were
left with these with these values and
these ways of enactment but without that
unifying star that's either that really
that really rumbled me when he said that
well and the the exchange has been more
complicated because of course CS lewis
CS lewis and the last book he wrote
which was the discarded image goes into
the model of the cosmos that was the
medieval model which was inherited in
many ways from the classical model and
so you know it's we like to think about
history as the seamless transitions when
and really so you had you had you know
greco-roman paganism and then
christianity there are reasons that
christianity comes up and what was sort
of an in-house feud in the jewish
community becomes the tsunami in the
roman world which takes a couple of
hundred years to really gain steam but
be just really emerges in force in the
roman imagination and just basically
cleans paganism zkk lock and the the
pagans that write about it are so
frustrated because the Christians are
just winning by virtue of their love and
their generosity and the pagans have no
weapon against this which is exactly
what the Apostle Paul says there's no
weapon that's formed against this yeah
and there's no law against this love and
that so then of course that's that
happens in the the Roman period the late
Roman period but then the the
Christianization of Europe which happens
in the collapse of the Roman period I
mean that takes hundreds of years and
and there's they're still with many
conversations this well that's from
Christianity that's
paganism a lot of it in in many ways
trying to becomes together and the and
I'll get in trouble with this with some
people but I always get in trouble and I
don't seem to mind but the you know what
what happens is that Christianity has
this capacity to infiltrate these other
cultures and religions and you know that
doesn't always go well but you know
people don't seem terribly bent out of
shape by Christmas trees and celebrating
Christmas and December and some of these
things which which clearly had
influences from other traditions but
Christianity has always had this
capacity to the Christianity that is
growing and being practiced let's say
and in mainland China today American
Christians on one hand celebrate that
rise but when they meet Christians
they're they're like well wait a minute
they've got these other ideas and the
same things happening in Africa now and
so I mean it's this has happened in the
past and continues to happen and so if
you read you know st. Maximus the
Confessor or Christian history or or
other people from the past you get this
sense of well I the symbols there and
the names are there but there are there
are other things which are which are
quite different
I remember reading you know doing a
little bit more in-depth work on agustin
you know the how Agustin sort of married
Christianity and Neil and neoplatonism
together just fascinating but this is
this has happened time and time and time
again over the years and that's it's it
hasn't stopped yet but you're right
these things get into us deep and and we
we don't they don't let us go so it's
it's uh what do you what do you make of
the the tendency it seems part of the
cat as you're saying part the
characteristic of Chris
is he doesn't seem to be able to get in
there right and he does like so you know
it's not always good and it is good a
lot of the time but what what is it
about Christianity that seems to be able
to kind of get in there in these
different ways in flourish well III
speaking as a Christian pastor I think
cuz it's true
and and that's just what happens with
truth yeah where you just can't get
around it at some point and I was
listening to Jonathan pujo did a
conversation with I don't remember his
name but I probably talked to him at
some point he was studying rené girard
and I mean Gerard is an interesting
figure but there's this there's this
there these dynamics that happened and
we see this sort of being played out in
our culture now with people posturing
with victim status and in order to gain
status and all of this stuff that's
going on and it it they're they're just
certain and jordan peterson talked about
this and i remember one of the things he
said about archetypes which he said you
know the thing about thinking about
these archetypes is you just don't get
beneath them you just get to the point
where you realize okay here's the story
where the a man who is god becomes the
servant of all he and his life shows
amazing power and yet is dies the most
humiliated victim and political loser
that you could imagine in the symbolism
of the period you know it's you you know
there's nothing higher than God and
there's you know you have the worst
punishment that you can have where
you're not just killed but you're
humiliated and it's public and anyone
who wanted to presuppose that you have
political aspirations well this is the
death of messiahs you know you know
nobody likes their Messiah is killed or
captured they want their messiahs
victorious and
so there's this story has within it a
capacity that you can't really get
beneath it yeah and and you know I
always I always think about the fact
that when Jesus sets up his disciples
and tells them to bring a sword to the
garden and then when Peter does with the
sword what everyone would expect is how
a sword could be used Jesus tells him to
put it away and then heals the man that
Peter struck and in a sense what Jesus
is saying in that garden is if if
there's any blood that's going to be
shed it will be mine now who says that
yes you know hey yes yes yeah I know and
that goes so deep right so did go so
deep and he walks into a political and
people often are not aware of the the
political religious culture war that
Jesus was born into but you know
basically the definition of losing in a
war like that is death and Jesus
basically walks into his death and says
I am going to win this war by dying and
it's like but that's not how you win
wars you win wars by by killing and
Jesus says no I am going to become I'm
going to be from the son of man which is
a a title out of the Book of Daniel I am
going to become the king of the world by
losing and everybody listens to that and
says that's just crazy talk but then
because everybody imagines he's going to
conquer Rome by building an army and
killing Romans and Jesus says no I'm
going to conquer Rome by dying as their
victim and that's exactly what happens
and it's like yes how does that happen
okay that's a weird historical and Alan
an AMA Lee it can't happen again but it
keeps happening yeah and so and and so
you know I there's this terrific novel
by a Japanese it was turned into a movie
I know if you've ever read it called
silence where the Jesuits go to Japan
and they're converting people and
Japanese authorities they've seen enough
of this and they want to get rid of all
the foreign influence which means the
farm religion and so basically they're
really savvy about it and they say okay
well this is how we're gonna handle the
priests we're going to put to death the
villages of the that the priests have
converted and that they love unless they
renounce their faith publicly by
stepping on this fool me hmm and so this
novel is about a priest who who you know
now is stuck at well I can save the
village by denying my lord and deny my
faith which will destroy the
evangelistic efforts and and should I
you know go to the go well it'd be one
thing if they were gonna kill him for
his fate but they're gonna kill the
village for his faith and so it's a then
Jesus Jesus in the in the symbol of this
Fumi speaks to the man and says trample
me trample me it's for this reason I
came into this world to be trampled and
that's just it just inverts everyone's
assumption about power and life and
Jesus says that he says if you want to
if you want to hold on to your life you
will lose it
yeah but if you lose it for my sake you
will find it and it just can't invert
that and so that's why Jesus just
persists right right so interesting so
interesting you know it is stunning
- I often think about um what the Romans
would make of the the make of like this
this cult
emerging right well I just would imagine
it wasn't even like that they and my
understanding is it it wasn't even like
that they didn't necessarily saw
initially the Christians is threatening
they just didn't
understand what they were doing they're
like wait a minute you're giving to the
huh like it it wasn't even like it was
opposite of what they were doing it was
just so radically different right that
it must have looked just looked insane
from their point of view yeah on some
level yeah Tom Holland has a new so he's
a he's a Roman historian he has a new
book coming out that talks about this
because if you know in antiquity if you
were a pagan and you saw a week or a
poor person well you know there's no if
you're weak well you were born to it and
it's your own fault
so you know pay pay the price and
Christians come along and just invert
that and the Romans well what do you do
with the people who let themselves be
killed right and you know they had seen
that in Masada let's say where everyone
on the mountain you know there's this
revenge suicide well you can kind of
understand that there's still pride in
that
but it's no just go ahead and you run
out of the village when there's a plague
we'll stay and we'll not only care for
our family who are sick will care for
yours yeah and of course those who live
yes yeah well what are they gonna do you
know they're just overwhelmed with
gratitude and you just can't stop that
and of course the the the weakness of
Christianity almost always comes when
Christians are given power because we
succumb to all of the normal temptations
of power right and then bad things
happen yeah I really like the one of the
things that I am i liked about about the
way that for baekje described
Agathe agape like this notion of and
this is where i was when i was listening
to
I was struck by the work what you know
the work that I do is I developed
something called circling that's kind of
now all over the world and I'm still
understanding I'm still understanding
exactly what it is
however this notion that agape actually
makes it unconcealed and makes people
yeah you know just this idea that like
this principle of where the Roman
citizens right the people who were
people were the ones who had power and
everyone else was slaves and they didn't
you know is brutal
and then here's here's this guy Jesus
who's evoking this deep unearned love
right this transcendent love where it's
just like he literally allows everyone
to become a person that sense of that
particular power of that and I and that
really put the language a lot of these
deep experiences that I've been having
for years circling with people because
put one of the things about circling is
it's it's you know it you could say you
could say that circling is a it's a
practice of essentially essentially
practicing the basic presuppositions and
could say asanas if you will of whatever
it is that makes for profound kind of
life-changing conversations right so
it's it's it's secular it's not
religious however it's interesting
people who do it enter our into it end
up using these very spiritual terms and
I think it's precisely because of this
deep sense of a kind of a gothic love
that they experience which like some of
the some of the vocabulary that's come
out of circle and some of the grammars
is this notion of being deeply seen
right this experience where people have
they come out they're like oh my god
I've never been seen so deeply in my
life and and I think what they're tuck
they're describing is something very
similar to that that unlike that that
sense of love that that parents have a
lot of right and that's one of the
things for Ricky talked about if you
exist and you have an identity and
you're a person it is because of a
gothic love right if you did if that
weren't there because you can't the
person can't earn it right if there's
any transaction in there it's not a
gothic love and so there's this quality
of that where you start in a circle is
that your your intention and where you
sit is basically like we bring our
attention to one person and we just
begin to relate to them as a person
right and and then people have these
experiences of like deep reverence in
these deep insights and these deep love
and there's this mutual kind of
transformational experience that they
they come out they come out of and I
think about I think about circling is a
kind of in a certain sense analogous to
something like a yogic practice where
you know like Ryoga is is on some on
some level you're just doing these these
mind-body postures that are these
archetypes if you will for every other
posture and mind coordination that you
have in your normal life and so you go
and do these deep stretches you know
these extreme things where you like you
know you coordinate your body you
strengthen and you lengthen not not so
much so that you can go and like do
downward dog on your desk at work
right it's so that when you're not
thinking about it you inhabit the
different areas in your life and your
baseline is just more open and what's
interesting to me is that especially
given like how primary like relationship
you mean relationships are almost
everything for us right that there
hasn't really been many practices that
are actually about just the fundamental
I thou connection that circling happens
to be and so what often happens is that
people go into it like a weekend or an
evening or they go through a course with
it and then they they go into these deep
stretches and then they have they go off
in their life and then they come back
the next day or they get these phone
calls and they're like yeah I went home
and I realized oh my god I've never
actually seen my wife before I never
actually saw my like as a person yeah
and this and I think that's telling
about what what you're stretching and
one of the things I've appreciated about
your videos and the place that you come
from is I can I appreciate how deeply it
seems to me that you you were grounded
in a fundamental care in people like
you're really like you're really you're
really open to people right and in such
a way in the particularity of people and
like there's like almost like an
unprejudiced miss about it right even in
even in in like that you're opening up
to this conversation right and you're
talking and you're sharing yourself but
you're also interested in such a way
something about the way you participate
with people and your orientation with
people um I recognize that because I
very much I very much feel like that I
in the last 20 years in doing circling
I've cultivated a lot of that sense of
being you people are just amazing like
people you're also awful
they're not neutral there's no no no
neutral no never never there's something
it's hard to put it's hard to put
identified exactly but there's a place
that you come from and meet individuals
and peoples that have a certain kind of
respect and reverence and an openness
that feels like unfortunately in my
experience more and more rare in the
world yeah I you know it's it's it's
fascinated me me and I don't wanna I
don't want to leave your story I kind of
want to get back to it because part of
the reason I always get into people's
stories and I'm sure you very much
understand this is because as you
mentioned as we began talking it's all
this contextual 'ti that I love when so
I did a little bit of commentary on
Brett Weinstein's talk with Alister
McGrath but when when Brett begins that
conversation he's dead on right and
saying that human beings have this
genetic material but we are so much
software yeah and and no one
you cannot birth a human being in a
test-tube because so much of how we are
and who we are our ability to function
we gain this from our parents and from
our context and and and it's you know
it's amazing
it's amazing how much good we can get
out of such terrible contexts but also
how much bad stuff we can pick up even
in such overwhelmingly good context I
mean those things are always there in
the middle yeah
and and I'm interested that I mean you
mentioned that you you got your you got
your start in massage school and now I
know a lot of people aren't probably
going to quite understand that but the
thing about if you're doing massage well
you're very sensitive to I mean that's
one of the things that you pick up
you're sensitive to someone else's body
which means that your problem
léa sensitive to them at a level that
they're not aware of yeah because
they're and our culture especially the
more the further we get down this
development track as we call it yeah
we're we're doing less and less with our
hands we're doing less and less work
with our bodies whereas say I remember
when I was a missionary in the Dominican
Republic one of the practices in the
church there was when we would do the
Lord's Supper communion there was always
foot washing at the beginning of that
because I was a missionary and I was
high and exalted and I really hated that
but they so I always had to wash
everyone's feet and the though I'd be
out way back in the stick somewhere and
we just have a circle of us because only
only only certain people could take the
Lord's Supper in these churches there
are always way more people looking on
then we're actually doing it and then we
all take off our shoes and then to hold
the feet of these often older men and
women who have lived most of their life
barefoot most of their life in on hills
and mountains scratching out a living
and you know their feet were often
pancaked calloused you know this world
had shaped and formed their feet and
then now I this young kid coming from
North America with a theology degree now
I am to wash their feet before we
partake of the body and blood which is
often some little crumbs of bread and
grape soda and and and this is and this
is what we're doing but as someone you
know beginning your career where you're
touching people's bodies they don't even
know what's going on in their bodies I'm
not surprised that this eventually then
worked into the audible massage we're
okay and and you know one of the things
that I've watched living here in
Sacramento is the you know the rise of
yoga in a community like this and I
one of the things that I see now it's of
course no mystery that the vast majority
of people in a place like Midtown
Sacramento that are at yoga studios tend
to be young white affluent women but the
disassociation that I think they are
attempting to you know attempting to
address in the practice mmm is something
that you know strikes me and that that
very much connects with okay so you've
got you know now you know the little
that I've sort of gleaned so far from
you and some of your videos about
circling the fact that in this society
people are not known and I think frankly
increasingly not even known as children
which was for many people the first the
first the first love that you would have
is the love of your parents yes and now
when you stroll through Target or
Walmart or go to eat in a restaurant how
many times don't I see a family sitting
at a meal in a restaurant you know the
kids are playing on a phone yeah parents
are either talking with each other or
they're on a phone and I'm thinking we
we have no I do
idea what we're doing to each other here
exactly well I think one of the things
that you get at I think one of the
consequences of this and I'm seeing this
more and more and I named because
because circling happens to be about a
practice about the fundamental unit of
relating I'm actually being exposed to a
lot of people in Silicon Valley that it
whether or not they're they oftentimes
they can't articulate it because we
don't have much language for it right
now but the reason why they're coming
there is because they there's a there's
a sense of that this tactile sense of
this intimate dance of encountering
another human being and staying with it
right is becoming more and more
it's such an earlier and earlier age ray
and this coordinated activity not even
just like just just not even the higher
levels of like what we're talking about
and conversation and stuff like that but
just the act of being in the presence of
another there's a there's so many things
that are being communicated including a
ship it like being in a shared social
practice that we're engaging it like
you're going like this I'm going like
this you know if I was like way up here
like this we would both you know you'd
also like hey there's a there's
something that we're feeling out and I
think that that back and forth is
literally the fundaments of our identity
is what will come to be our identity in
our personality and if you change any
part of that right at an early age
especially right and then a whole age in
a whole area this is why I think
technically we can get into the
technology thing in Heidegger because I
think it's eerily it's worth a very
eerie time if you begin to see it which
I think you're pointing to um but if you
change that at all all of a sudden
people stop they start occurring less
and less human so for example I had a
somebody a young a young guy he's like
25 I think he's in Silicon Valley he he
like he made it big in the like a
start-up and he doesn't have to work
anymore
and he tells me about like that he he
was in a relationship and that and how
he does all his relationship is he signs
he signs like a a one-month contract
with them like they make agreements you
have certain times that they meet and
they put it all in their calendar on
their phone and he was talking to me
like this and I thought it was joking as
it apparently apparently this is like
not unusual for the people that he hangs
out with
really yeah the instrumentation
and the the calculating kind of stick
store ality of of something as a human
relationship right is becoming more more
in framed right yeah and he's in and I'm
noticing with a lot of the people that
I'm running into who like the millennial
generation whatever the next one is is
they they really they're the this the
the ability to hang in this coordinated
awkward ambiguously and big ambiguity
filled thing called inner subjectivity
yeah is they're they're less and less
coordinated and in so much of so much of
what's obvious to me isn't obvious to
them right it's really it's really
telling and I think I think you know of
course here in the Bay Area we see the
beginnings of what ends up becoming
throughout so it's like god I feel sad
about it yeah yeah you know my wife my
wife teaches at a Waldorf School and
it's it's very interesting watching she
just started her at Walter school you go
one through eight and then you go back
down to first grade again and of course
the the Waldorf methodologies it's a
public school but the Waldorf
methodologies are very tactile very
relational from the beginning and it's
you know what's so interesting is that
these things were just normal not that
long ago and for the sake of other
things we have abandoned them without
understanding exactly what we're doing
to ourselves at that I you know I really
like what you just said in terms of okay
so so this this new couple is going to
have a relationship that will be
mediated by Google Calendar yes and and
this this very much gets into you know
throughout the history of the world now
we've had what what is so generically
described as development so we have the
underdeveloped countries or the
developing world and the developed world
without giving much thought to what that
development is and what its shape is and
so that's one of the things that I often
run into in my profession as pasture
because pasture is one of the few
remaining professions that at least in
small churches not in large churches in
small churches remains rather
undeveloped so last Friday we were you
know stripping the floor in the
sanctuary and relaxing it and so I had a
hand in that and and so when you know
people will come to me with just about
any problem that you can imagine and so
the pastor role is sort of analogous to
say a parent role because it isn't
mediated or bounded whereas a more
contemporary analogies of course let's
say a therapist who we sit in this box
we have 50 minutes there are you know
you can say anything but the therapist
was gonna be very careful about their
own disclosures yeah and you know how
different from people will often watch
my videos and they say well you're doing
therapy it's like no I'm doing something
that's a lot older than therapy oh yeah
you know what I'm mostly doing is
listening even when you said like I
could just feel I could just feel when
he said this I could feel myself drop
into this kind of deeper sensibility of
oh yeah I was hanging out I was doing
the floors with them right I had a hand
in it this kind of notion of like
getting in with people and like getting
a hand in their lives and this hanging
with somebody for long periods of time
working next to them hammering
and helping them with things and that
level of involvement less and less like
most of that is is being out sourced
right our sense of our hands because I
want to get one of the big things I was
thinking about is is you know they talk
about like well how the hell did we get
frontal lobes well it's because of our
hands right it's because of our thumbs
in that it and the question is is like
you know is it was the is the is our the
hands for the frontal lobes and I think
at first at first they were for the
hands but as time goes on less and less
of the enactment in the in the working
with something right struggling through
something being with ambiguity and like
all that sensibility is become less and
less unless we don't even have buttons
on our phones given those are virtual
right now we have to say well seems like
it seems like we did a dyslexic move
right it's more like the frontal lobes
are have taken over and dominated the
whole thing right you no longer need our
hands so so how did you make the
transition from hands into talking they
that's a great it's a great question
it's funny cuz no one's actually ever
picked up on that in what I've talked
about it's interesting to tell like
because no one's ever really like kind
of picked up on that this connection
between massage and and in talking so
just that in itself I think is kind of
points to what I am experienced with you
that stands out to me right of like this
kind of sensibility of I don't what
whatever that you know whatever it is
that we're talking about but there's
well and the reason I say it is because
this is how we are you didn't just you
know when you were in Arizona massage
school you didn't say I'm gonna in
Phillips I'm going to develop circling
and we're gonna do this I mean my
chances
most everything almost anything
successful that we do we usually sort of
stumble into it and it's from one thing
to another and and oh my goodness I
didn't expect to do this so I'm curious
how this came about in your life yeah
exactly
well it's interesting because I've
always had this well both metaphorically
and literally a good touch that's like
things that like to touch an object
right the way you touch an object is is
a completely different thing than when
you touch somebody right you touch
somebody is always a communication so
it's like so there's so many different
levels that are going on and you can
always tell a good massage therapist
from a bad one from the moment they're
very initial touch this is like a really
good one they can just just grab your
finger and you feel that they're in
consideration of the whole of your body
you can you feel your whole body grasp
whereas like somebody who's not then you
just they grab an object right that's
right so that particular kind of tuning
into something and being oriented around
it I would have to say God I could if
ITIF I kind of feel back into it there's
a way I would say there's there was
there was a way in which so so where i
grew i grew up both my parents who are
like they're both they're both
extraordinary people they're amazing
people and and they suffer from
addiction and you know there was like a
lot of craziness and like you know
violence and all kinds of all the things
that come with addiction we suffered
sure when i was a kid and i was an only
child and so there was a way in which oh
like I was often from a very early age
was I was kind of managing the fights
between my mom and my dad right and I so
there would be this kind of way in which
where I could kind of feel the way my
dad pulled into the driveway I could
kind of feel into like what kind of mood
he was in right so there's there's a
there was a way where I think a lot of
my resources were were feeling into
things right in such a way that we're
feeling into things in a way where I
wasn't necessarily subjugating myself to
the to the conflict that's right of
course I wasn't very sexist successful
at that but like you know kind of
feeling into a mood like being with all
of my mother's hurts and all of that so
there was a kind of way where intuitions
were earned yeah yeah absolutely
absolutely as a child in a context like
that
yes survival tell me if not physically
emotionally Oh totally so what you say
doesn't surprise me a bit yeah so I
think it's like there's something about
there's something there's something
about in there that had me kind of
extend myself out right and feel into
things so there's something about the my
physical embodied orientation to it is
is has a deep courtesy to it and like
remaining invisible in some regard yet
yet in deep consideration of the other
so I've never actually put I've never
really thought about it quite like that
in the way that you asked it but it that
actually kind of makes sense to me
I'd say that there's also something
there about one of the like really
wonderful things about my childhood is
my grandparents now my grandfather my
grandfather was something else man he
was something else he was he came to
he's I don't know if this is true or not
he was like he was storyteller but
credible man he came to he came to the
United States
in 1928 used to say I came here with
only 50 cents in my pocket from Germany
he's from Hanover Germany and he was
born he was he was born into a family on
the farm right outside of Hannover
Germany he had 17 brothers and sisters
Wow are you that any that he talked
about like he didn't want to get stuck
on the farm so he somehow escaped the
family and he lived he lived in the park
and apprenticed under a tailor for a
couple of years and then he found a boat
to San Francisco to to the United States
and that's how he got there and he
started something called he started a
business called Hoff cleaners and Chuck
Comiskey of you know Comiskey Park I was
like you used to bring his clothes in to
get dry clean and my grandpa did his
suits and there's a whole historical
piece there and my grandpa was this
really outgoing man very like very
colorful like this great sense of humor
and he was deeply German right um and he
was a strange father but as a
grandfather he was almost like he and he
had a base my remember had a basement
right and he collected everything and
coins and stuff like just he click he
was like one of the top amateur
photographers in the world he'd filmed
the first tiger fight ever caught on
film in the Amazon he's just a really
interesting guy um and for whatever
reason out of all but like the cousins
and relatives and stuff like that he he
just kind of he picked me and he just
basically picked me and he just what I
like to say is the part of him that like
dwells in the basement right all of his
creativity he just poured all of it on
me and he had a three acre yard and he
had I remember you had wild geese right
and he'd like he'd put me outside and
the geese would chase me and geese
me they are they are like yeah like but
there is a way in which there was a way
where I remember he would pick me up
from school and he take me home until my
parents would you know pick me up in the
evening and I I I had all kinds of
learning disabilities I'm Dyslexic
and no one could get me to do my
homework no one could quite get me out
of my imagination didn't learn how to
like to read till I was like 11 or 12
and so I would have all these rules of
trying to get me to read and I my
grandpa would come home and he just take
all these rules and just kind of throw
it down he's like alright what do you
want to do and he just wherever my
interest went mmm
like he just made space for it and he
just like that's all of his interested
in is following my imagination wherever
my curat he would just set up scenarios
you didn't care if I got glue on the
floor he would let me watch anything and
there was something about something
about my relationship with him mmm that
I think if I oftentimes think about this
if it wasn't for him I don't know
exactly would I be like if I would still
even be alive you know yeah so there's
this kind of a way there was a what
there was a reverence and a think an
embodiment of I would say what do you I
think what he what he transmitted to me
was a deep deep deep sense of wonderment
mmm because he was an extraordinary and
extraordinarily am NOT curiosity right
but wonderment something like a lot more
primary primordial and he just had this
way of meeting the world where he was
there was an like an openness to it and
there's something he related to me
through that man I grew up in that until
I was like so we moved away to Arizona
so that it was like what was that for
you leaving him oh my gosh
it was it was I would say it was that
experience of leaving him probably and
what opened up for me in that it's
probably the thing that even has us
having this conversation right now
like it was I had an experience of like
a kind of an existential ontological
floor dropping out my parents got sober
and they they kind of realized that they
couldn't stay sober in Chicago so we
moved to some friends lived in
cottonwood arizona and leaving my
grandparents now I had no
conceptualization for it at the time but
what I started to have are these extreme
panic attacks like where I would just
feel yeah you know but however Vicki
talks about like that where he talks
about horror right that sense of like
things aren't what what I thought that
they were yeah I would just go I would
have like a like a bottom dropping out
experience in this this this icy cold
feelings of dread that would come over
my body and I'd start crying and I
couldn't talk about why yeah and of
course you know there's nothing I don't
know if there's anything one of the
things they say the only thing crazier
than active drug drug addicts and
alcoholics or newly sober was so I'm
just like I've just no idea what's going
on I really at that point I just didn't
have any emotional safety with my
parents how old were you I was like I
think it was like 11 or 12 wow wow wow
well what this is what's really
interesting and is then my parents got
really involved in a yeah which is a
religion of sorts I remember this moment
because this is this is like a moment I
think it was we
moved in and I'm having these panic
attacks and I don't even know what they
are and I can't talk to my parents and
I'm having obsessive-compulsive thoughts
over and over again and I remember one
day early when we first moved it was
either an a a meeting that they were
having out on her front porch or maybe
it was just like they had a gathering of
the of the people that were in the
fellowship that they were getting to
know and I just like went outside and
just sat down and sent the conversation
and I remember distinctly that was like
it was like my life was one way and then
this happened and there was another way
i sat down and I just started to like
tune into what they were talking about
and it was it's interesting because up
until that point about every
conversation I've ever had had been
always talking about like kind of what
you had what other people had what you
didn't have what you're doing what they
were doing what you should do right
especially in the Midwest like the
Midwestern like my uncle I go back now
my my aunt talked about like the Kirby
vacuum cleaner she just got three and a
half hours right it's like those are the
only conversations I've ever actually
experienced this was like a conversation
that was unlike any other conversation
and it was like it occurred to me like a
different world and it was the first
time I had ever heard people talk about
what it what had them experience what
they were experiencing like what had
them see how they were seeing like that
that that there was some there was seem
to they presuppose that there's some way
that I participate with reality that
that has it show up for me the way that
it does right there's this whole other
world that opened up that was part of
the conversation and I experienced it as
something a completely different
dimension almost and and whatever it was
that they were talking about whenever
that opened
had I knew had some connection between
this bottom dropping out sensation that
was going on with me and I didn't know
how I couldn't conceptualize it at the
time but I just could feel it and I just
was like all right I'm gonna go there
and I like entering in that conversation
and I haven't come out since you know
that that's again that I mean that's so
helpful I one of the things I loved
about what John did with using an
addiction with his video series is his
understanding addiction as you know this
what you lose as you lose agency yeah
and so you had two parents who were
struggling with addiction I mean the
fact that you're alive at all well
that's pretty good
ran your and the fact that you came out
of that as a semblance of a whole human
being highly attributable to your
grandfather who I don't know but I would
guess that part of the reason he chose
you was he had an understanding that you
needed him very well me yeah and and so
and then your parents getting sober you
know you in a sense you know you you had
to get sober to whether or not you had
anything to drink because again when
when the parents are in that diminished
state their children you know they're
they're they're along for the ride yeah
and and so I can very much understand
you know I've known a lot of people who
have come through AAA and AAA which you
know obviously comes out of the Oxford
groups and and that whole movement even
deeply Christian movement oh yeah and
and so I'm not at all surprised that oh
my gosh so yeah you got to get out if
you're gonna get sober a lot of people
do you got to break those networks you
need new networks and they got they and
they have to be you know they have to be
and they have to be in the Church of AAA
and and they didn't have a young
people's group but you needed to be
there too so it
that surprises me and then again also to
to understand you know with the distance
so I was this I'm Dyslexic to but not
severely and but I you know to
understand then okay massage that that
makes that makes all the sense in the
world and then you know well well okay
so the body and but now also the mind
and the heart and the self and the you
know it makes it makes all the sense in
the world that in many ways to a in in
in the pre developed pre-industrial
world obviously there were many there
are many sadnesses and sorrows that
afflicted humanity yeah but in some ways
much of the much of the therapy was just
simply built into the planet yeah you go
out and you work that soil yeah and you
and you and and you grow the plant or
you husband the animal and you I mean so
so those rhythms and the life that are
all built in and what happens with
industrialization is that well well
increasingly where people become tools
of other people and always had that with
serfdom to a certain degree but now
within a machine world they literally
become tools they've become machine
operators extensions of the machine and
and and then also in terms of the
mind-body thing we just keep floating
away from ourselves yeah and and so the
fact that we have many many people who
you know I've heard people say things
like well well that person looks at home
in their body and whenever I hear that
I'd always think well where else would
they be but this is this is exactly
what's what's what we've been doing to
ourselves and each other yes and it's
also I would say to that the connection
because now you have to be thinking
about what is this connection between
like touch and what I'm doing now
and I think I think maybe one of the one
of it has to do with like listening um
because my one of these my grandfather
was he was a storyteller so was my dad
my dad's my dad's my dad's awesome
they're actually they're both still
sober
there have been sober wonderful they're
that they're awesome
yeah they're awesome I'm you know the
the the life after them being sober
versus before it's almost like two
different realities um however my
grandfather he I would listen to his
stories over and over and over and over
again it didn't even matter right that
he told me I've heard all of them eighty
thousand times but I always and that's
something also to do with the north
being the only child I think it's hard
to describe but I think that there's to
relate your relationship with the adults
around you when you don't have other
kids I think that there's some kind of
like something that goes on there that I
I'm not sure but I haven't the I think
it did for me where I would every day
when he would pick me up from school
right
like I would hear him talk about stories
right over and over and over again right
and and I would show up for him and the
same thing with my dad I would always I
would bug him because I had tons of
questions all the time was constantly
asking him questions about this in his
life and that his life to hear the
stories and so there was this way in
which listening for me was something
that was deeply deeply in my life right
and so then when we so then when we
started to go and be in a well what's
like well if you look at it well how do
they do it well you get together right
they set a context right and then what
do they do they share yeah nothing and
they share the most unbelievable things
that they're not going to share any
place else yeah exactly exactly and so
like I would go to all the open a
meetings and like I do every way I all I
wanted to do is be around these people
and so starting at you know where I was
11:12 all i wanted to do is be around
all the people that were older than to
me because i could he start to hear and
especially we gotta a there were stories
that were like starting to be linked to
these deeply personal things but also
these trans personal things yeah and
there's like just the ritual of doing
that over and over and over and over
again that has always like evoke such
deep I would say connectedness of of
just hearing kind of like how incredible
people are and how incredible people's
anything of what it is is stepping in in
to embody being able to through your
listening being able to actually embody
someone else's perspective and see it
see from their from their perspective
which is the participating and seeing in
that way is what grants gives us a sense
of presence so I think I've just had a
like uh this this connection between
listening really getting other people's
perspectives and participating in that
way is linked to this I think for me
that the that orientation really allows
something cut to come into presence and
be filled with sense and you can tell
kind of the way I use my hands and stuff
like this that it's very it's very
structural and like kind of getting a
grip on something it's very very
embedded with like listening and
embodying and walking in someone else's
shoes that allows so much more of the
world to kind of show itself on deeper
and deeper dimensions mm-hmm Thanks
fight I had never quite really even
thought about like explicitly made that
connection between massage and listening
and everything that we're talking about
is a completely new angle thank you
that's why I think it's just helpful to
that we tell our stories oh yeah because
every time we tell
it's yeah we see we see another aspect
and even in the repetition of telling it
yes we discover new things yes oh I
don't know if you want to talk more
about circling or I've kind of been pest
I mean when we get on these
conversations I kind of get into
pastoral mode and start probing but I
don't want to be a be a one-sided probe
or I don't know if there's things that
you'd like to we've got another half
hour so so we've got plenty of time yeah
you bet
well what I think it's one of the things
about even just like what happened right
here now is he like you're like oh the
massage school and hearing my story and
then all of a sudden I'm the logos
starts to gather together right like the
sense of just you know we come in
together in this conversation seems to
like the logos comes in and kind of
reveals both the ground and a new
horizon right and then the ground that
personal but there's a way in which it's
like you you're interested in me
personally that personal connection that
you have right that I can see and just
your the way that you talk with people
right your interest with people and then
watching and then what what this is one
of the things that I was gonna ask you
about too is that you see I've heard you
use this term a bunch of times um having
conversation partners right having
conversation partners and it's always
struck me as as like having conversation
partners it's an unusual way of saying
that it struck two because usually it's
usually like you know when people talk
about it's like oh yeah and a friend and
we had this conversation right there is
this like yeah me and my wife we had
this conversation but there's a way that
you just kind of use the term I just
wanted to kind of like explore this with
you where you're like it seems that
you're Cano ting on
some level that there's conversation and
that other people join us in it and I
and it seems to be very related I would
imagine it to like all these people that
you're meeting online right in the
videos what do you make of that that's
like when you say conversation partners
like and what's been the impact of these
kinds of conversations on you on me well
part of the reason I use the word
partners is because we're building
something yeah each conversation and now
especially that they're now especially
that I'm recording them and putting them
on the internet which is sort of a crazy
thing but we're you know just just as we
began talking about a human being is not
just this this physical creature but
it's this embodied contextualized story
being and so with each conversation we
are in fact we are building something
we're building something between us
right now
something's being did it's a
continuation of the building in you it's
the continuation of the building in me
you know it's it's striking it's
striking that most of what we have about
Jesus which simply by virtue of texts is
limited but most of what we have with
Jesus are his interactions with people
mhm and interesting you know that the
when I was so I grew up obviously and my
father was a minister and my father I
had this weird bicultural growing up
where the church that my father was was
shepherding was mostly a black church
and then the ethnic group that I came
out of which this crazy Dutch Reformed
thing that had schools so I went to
K through 12 with about a hundred other
kids that you know small kind of a small
town within a New York metropolitan area
and then the black community and so then
where was I going with this so you know
this was this is sort of the context in
which I grow up and this obviously that
and gets built into me and so all of
these stories get built in to me but but
Jesus in the Gospels tell all the
stories of all the different things that
yeah yeah yeah Dutch immigrant stories
you know then my father they're
pastoring which meant helping people and
all kinds of things so you know once I
got big enough that my father was
so-and-so has to move so it's like I'd
go with my father and we'd use kind of
the church suburban and move somebody
stove and fridge and you'd get into
people's houses and and and you'd see
life from that side so so so I grew up
in this and then I go to college and I
it's obviously a deeply Christian
upbringing and and very much learning
faith by watching the decisions that my
parents made for life and then then you
go to college and when you're in college
you get to kind of think on your own and
so then I sort of start reading the
Bible for the first time and really with
with different eyes because now I can
decide if I want to throw it away or
keep it yeah and I start reading the
Gospels these stories about Jesus and
their strange because there's all these
squabbles about dietary laws and healing
on Sunday and all of these things and
it's like what's what's this about why
on earth have for 2,000 years people
been reading these stories and saying
this is the most important book they can
read this is this is utterly strange mmm
you begin to realize that the especially
the Gospels are just once one
interaction story after another and you
know some of the most interesting ones
are sort of the one offs so Jesus has
his disciples
and that's a that's an interesting
relationship between them because here's
Jesus the Son of God getting frustrated
with the disciples and saying how long
do I have to put up with you he's only
with him for three years I've been with
this church twenty-one years so you know
if God could get frustrated well I
suppose we have a little bit of weakened
gains forgiveness for some of that but
but there's these stories like you know
one that I preached on a few weeks ago
where Jesus goes to the other side of
the lake which is a Gentile area and
there's this man with who is you know he
has an unclean spirit and that's a very
deep term in the Bible and when we say
demon-possessed we kind of put it in a
different frame when we do that but but
he's he's living amongst the tombs the
village has given up on him and I here
in in this area of Sacramento there are
a lot of group homes there are a lot of
homeless people I deal with people who
are usually mentally ill and
self-medicating with street drugs all
the time and and and so I very I deal
with a lot of unmedicated schizophrenic
and and so you know and I read that
passage and I imagine that this man
probably grew up in that town and you
know probably his mental illness you
know and so they tried in the Dominican
Republic there was one there was one
home by some friends of ours and we
would go and have dinner with them and
we just heard somebody screaming it said
well who's yelling
well that's the screamy guy well who's
the screamy guy well we don't know but
the parents keep him locked in his room
he's again he's probably got some mental
illness and they don't know how to deal
with him so they keep him locked in the
room and they shovel food in and it's a
third-world country that's how they're
managing it yeah oh here's this guy he's
living by the tombs they've tried to
chain him but he breaks the chains he
you know Jesus comes off the boat on the
wrong side of the lake and he runs to
Jesus and says the craziest thing you
know he says you know get away from me
because I know who you are and then
Jesus starts talking to him and and and
most of the conversation isn't recorded
because probably the disciples are
what the heck is going on here we follow
this crazy man around and the nuttiest
stuff happens we're fascinated with them
but we don't understand it yeah and then
you know Jesus you know Jesus then talks
to the spirit and says what's your name
I am legion for we are many don't kill
us don't throw us into the abyss throw
us into those pigs and Jesus says okay
go to the pigs they go into the pigs and
then the man and then the man is you
know then all the villagers who are
watching the pig see pigs do very
something unpick the pigs which was a
sane pig would never do this the pigs
thousands of them run into the sea and
drown and so then the villagers are like
there goes the economy did this and then
they go and find this Jesus guy who came
from the other side of the lake and his
group of friends along with this guy
that they know so well who everyone the
best they could do was banish him from
the down and try and shame him and he's
living in caves which are probably tombs
and there he said stressed and in his
right mind dick who is last thing you
just said and there is this crazy man
sitting dressed yes and in his right
mind and so here are the people of the
village they just watched the pigs all
drown themselves they just see this guy
who's now they've all known to avoid
because he's a madman but now he's
sitting and having a rational
conversation with this other guy who
started this and then the the man who
was you know possessed says to Jesus can
I come with you and Jesus says no you
have to stay here with your town in the
community and it's like hmm so here's a
conversation and so I'll you read the
Gospels and it's just one conversation
after another well what on earth is
Jesus doing well what he's doing is
actually helping reknit people together
not only in terms of their selves but
their towns and their families and their
communities he's actually reading the
world together and it's all happening
one conversation at a time and and yeah
they're they're the miracles and all of
that but you very much get the sense in
the
hospitals that the miracles are
illustrations to the message that he's
giving yes and so why do i well because
well this is my craft I'm a pastor it's
one conversation at a time and sometimes
the conversation is public to a room
with people we call that preaching
sometimes a conversation is a Bible
study me and about 10 people in a room
but often the conversation is like what
we're doing here and you know this is
this is how you know I find it you know
we began this conversation by noting
that human beings need each other so
deeply just to survive otherwise we're
not really human and ravais keys I mean
when I saw that video I thought wow this
is one of the best articulations of
Agape that I've heard where actually and
it's it's just true it's it's the
mothers it's the mother's sacrifice of
herself and the father's sacrifice of
himself that creates a human being and
your grandfather's sacrifice of himself
yeah probably looking at this kid and
saying boy the parents are struggling
and this kid needs help and I'm gonna
pour my life into this kid yeah and
that's that's how we live that's how you
know and and so and so then it'll also
begin at the beginning we talked about
you know why Christianity well here at
the center of it is a man who lives his
life he's saying the world's well being
at his personal expense and and no child
no healthy child comes into the world
without someone in their world pouring
out their life into this child and and
part of the reason you know it's so
funny because we have this conversation
about immigrants you know and I find the
most sane people in America to be the
immigrants so often is the Americans
that are nuts that come from these
countries but at least they had a father
or a mother who poured into them
and and they know you know they know how
to how to love a child and it's the it's
so often the immigrants who are working
these minimum-wage jobs and American
nursing homes who are changing the
diapers and washed and giving the sponge
baths too you know our parents and aunts
and uncles and you know so well how do
we connect well I think it's the touch
yeah it's it's it's the meeting of I
mean we're a conversation that that John
verb a key did with Benjamin Boyce was
it's actually one of my favorite
conversations of John's we're where John
talks about the fact it's something that
I've been thinking about for a long time
you know well what am i well in many
ways the the I that I associate with
myself is this autobiography that sort
of started with myself when I was like
three or four and you yourself mentioned
a moment you only had a moment like this
I can remember a moment like this in my
past where you reach a certain point of
sort of self-awareness
you know the autobiography has started
then you reach a point of self-awareness
and you begin to realize oh my goodness
and and in that self conversation of
self-awareness you kind of locate
yourself in the midst of other persons
and and in the midst of a world and and
and that's what we are now obviously we
began before that but it was love that
in a sense brought us to that point and
it was the sacrifice you know the the
the good parent sacrifices themselves
for their child in wise ways because
there are obviously the there there are
things that look like sacrifice which
really aren't and kids learn that
eventually my kids lately have been
watching um if some of them are home for
the summer from college and they're
watching Arrested Development and you
just watch that family and you just say
oh we are such we are so adept at fall
to cover ourselves and and try to
achieve status cheaply and all of this
but no so one and so when I started
doing this channel you know the first
thing I thought I was just fascinated by
Jordan Peterson and what was happening
around him and I was fascinated by the
fact that people were watching Jordan
Peterson and getting interested in
religion and I thought well isn't that
strange and so then I started making
videos and then suddenly I've got all
these emails and requests for to talk to
me mm-hm and so I start doing I start
talking to people and I start talking to
people on skype and then I realize after
talking to a number of people I bet you
some other people would benefit by
listening to the conversation and so
they usually only about half of the
conversations yeah people say yeah I'd
be willing to share that yeah and then I
throw it up on YouTube it's like we'll
see what happens right and then I and
then you know a bunch of people only
watch the videos that I produce to talk
about Jordan Peterson or verbe key or
whatever but another group of people say
I always I cut this from my mother
because my mother said I only watch the
conversations and I thought huh isn't
that interesting
you know she's changed my mother loves
me and she's proud of her son and all
those things but the videos where I
ramble on about Jordan Peterson play but
who's he talking to
yes what's their story yes how does that
help me right great
did you know one of the things that I
I'm one of the things I'm really
interested in is looking at this
phenomena right oh because I think what
we're doing or this part of the internet
right of where you know you heard lots
of different people talk about this but
we're it for the first time right we
you're able to like have these long
during difficult conversations that no
one would think would to it into right
but it turns out that that not only are
people tuning into it but they're
they're being affected in such deep ways
and so what I'm hearing you say actually
because it's interesting I really
appreciated the way that you you just
teased out not just not just the the
conclusion of the of the Bible right of
the stories but the structure of it like
there's another level of like meaning
that came out I'd never quite looked at
it like that I haven't read the Bible a
whole a whole bunch but like I've never
heard anybody could quite talk about it
like that but oh yeah that's what he
does it's like Jesus goes around and he
has conversations and then it shows an
impact of those conversations that
seemed to make things better right
like just that's it that's a really it's
a really cool observation or a very cool
thing to hear and in some way I mean I
think what we're inside of is one of the
few places where technology is bringing
something that is fundamentally not
technological yeah right and I think has
a lot to do with this this experience of
listening and if you think about like
the like just the phenomenology of
listening is just fascinating when you
get into it right because because
listening connecting to hearing
Heidegger kind of weaves the etymology
all the way back into the original like
the oldest notion that he could find was
that listening is very connected to
sacred obedience hmm and if you think
about it obedience it's kind of a
strange word but like when you think
about to really obey something like it's
you can't you can't you can't force the
kind of like deep obedience it's like it
takes all of your freedom right to deep
obey to something who were harkening
right to hearken to something and
although it's video really at least at
this with a conversational form it's
really what you're doing is listening
and what if you look at the
phenomenology of listening it's really
interesting because if you look at just
in terms of like sense capacities right
I can I can I can listen to you and I
can I can touch and still listen right I
can look around and still listen right I
can smell and still listen but but I
can't listen to you and think right it's
really interesting it's like if I try to
listen to you and you start thinking
about yeah all of a sudden I'm like well
if you look at this right and I think
about the notion of life there's some
videos and and and things I've listened
to that I have gone back over and over
and over and over and over and over
again yeah if you think about this well
to fully listen is to fully let you
think the thought I'm fully being
obedient to the thought now if you look
at like for some thoughts what it takes
to be able to think that thought is
actually like especially when you get
into philosophy and religious and these
kinds of thoughts right in order to
think the thought in other words to
listen to you write some of these
thoughts require me to step on a
completely different preset position
right it rests on a different ground
that I'm not on such that like when I
try to think it the first time I watched
it the first time I'm like I'd I can
sense an other mnestheus there
something's good there but I don't quite
get it so you listen to it again you
listen to it again and at a certain
point and this is where I think
listening becomes transformational pray
is that like at some point you in order
to you you're able to like step on a
front presupposition right that allows
me to oh then think that thoughts right
and if you start changing your
presuppositions you start changing
everything right yeah like way that you
perceive and one of the things I've
noticed and I and I talked about this
was John this is part of our ongoing
text dialogue I had done an interview
and the person sent me the recording
earlier and I and I don't think we
talked explicitly about John or our
conference just a little bit and I
listened to it now I was listening to
you I was like Hello I said that in a
way I've never quite said that and that
she and I saw the impact of these
conversations I've been having with John
in and not what I was necessarily saying
explicitly but how the perspective I was
coming from and I didn't recognize it
until I listened to it again and so I
like you know I texted a month's okay
listen like I'm seeing the impact of our
conversations on how I'm seeing if you
change it's funny do you think about if
you start to change how you see how you
listen how you think how you perceive
now you're talking about your whole the
way that you meet the world the way that
you act yeah you know I so I'm kind of
getting the sense of like oh whoa
you know in in so many different ways
like listening to people like you John
you know all the different conversations
that I'm involved in the I'm being very
impacted right through in a certain
sense
harkening right and what it takes to
harken and this is very midden much also
my experience with reading Heidegger
right
so when you read Heidegger you don't
really you're not informed right like
that's not really read everything
Heidegger like you read Heidegger
because he takes you on a walk right and
you realize you realize that oh what he
was actually doing is he's taking on a
walk
around the lake and then all of a sudden
you start to realize that Oh in in not
understanding a word he said what it
took to try had me stand in a place that
he taught me how to see he taught me how
to listen and in reading Heidegger and
that's right when we were starting to do
circling right reading Heidegger and
doing circling I had no idea why cuz I I
can't read like I'm you know so I don't
know why I was like most things that
you're talking about I something seizes
my interest and I twenty years later I
discover why I was interested in it
right yeah and then behind that is a
whole career the language trail is a
digit or whatever yeah yeah I just I I
there's a there's a there's a way in
which I see you deeply engaged in this
as well right of like and just wondering
about what you think about that about
this whole thing about this this all of
a sudden we have this dimension in our
lives that is you're talking about it's
actually the the dimension itself isn't
new right like we've been all of us all
we've ever done is like talk and have
conversations however strangely enough
we're having less and less of those yeah
right in the way that we're talking
about it yeah at the same time there's a
piece of technology that is it's brought
a deeper a deeper way of listening or
the opportunity to listen at very very
deep levels to people that we wouldn't
have otherwise I I think that's right
and I I have since starting this thing
thought well what the thing that most
gratifies me the thing I find most
rewarding from my coming on two years of
doing things on YouTube
is that so so I was doing conversations
with people and then the same people
kept coming back to me for more
conversations and then new people I
couldn't have conversation with new
people and I thought I missed
Church pastor I've just started a very
small church because I'm going to keep
talking to these same dozen or two dozen
people and so I told them I said okay if
I've had two conversations with you you
can't sign up for another slot and then
they're all like what do we do and what
they did was they started a discord
server and they started YouTube channels
and they're all having conversations
with each other and so what actually
happened was in I because you realized
very quickly as a pastor you become a
bottleneck for the community
yeah when someone starts getting
interested in the church they want to
meet you and get to know you and maybe
be your friend and all that but you're
not really a pastor until they all get
to know each other and have
relationships with each other
yeah and so what happened was when I
kind of put the kibosh on okay I'm
putting a limit here they all started
talking to each other
sudden each other suddenly all of these
new YouTube channel started and new
meetup started and people are talking on
the discord server and it was like huh
that's that's because the thing is if if
they're if their growth is limited by
access to me I am actually now an
impediment to their growth right and and
so you know what I thought is that this
this YouTube thing is really a powerful
instrument and I agree with you
completely in that for for a lot in a
lot of ways it sort of been it's brought
us in the wrong direction because people
our kids are watching YouTube instead of
having conversations with their parents
but in this case I think this is a
redeeming use of it yeah but but also
one of the things so when I started
making videos one of the things just as
a pastor I knew that the videos on my
channel mostly are phases talking
because seeing each other's faces we
talk is really important yeah and when I
started making videos about Jordan
Peterson
I thought based on talking to people in
my local meetup a lot of people are
watching Peterson out there and they
no one to talk about anything that
they're learning with and if you and as
every teacher knows if you take
something in but you can't process it
either writing it out and your own words
are talking about it you're not gonna
learn it and so I decided that when I
started making videos I was going to
watch his videos with people well how
can I do that
well I watch twitch and people I saw
people are playing computer games and
people are watching other people play
computer games what's with that yeah
there's it's tons of people doing that
and it's like okay well we're lonely
we're disconnected and even though this
is oh it would be far more fun to be in
the room playing a game together because
again generally speaking women relate
face-to-face men relate side-to-side hmm
anyways I thought I'm gonna do videos
where people can watch me listening to
Jordan Peterson and it sounds crazy but
I thought no because there are many many
people out there in the world that are
all by themselves and this is second
best but sometimes second best is all
you got yeah totally no I think you're
right about you're very much right about
the listening it's one of the things I
learned so you become a pastor and you
think well I've got all this information
that I'm gonna give to people it's it's
and in pastoral care it's it's all
listening yeah in fact I would say for
me in encircling and training people out
a circle most of the the deep grappling
with philosophy and these kinds of
conversations if anything it's taught me
how to listen right all those all my
version of those books back there it's
like it's allowed me to it's yeah
there's something about sit like if I'm
able to like actually hear the author
and get get these distinctions right
because the more distinctions that you
have and the more you practice being
able to make distinctions right the more
you can hear the more
you see I can only relate to something
Ivan that's distinct right so this
quality I think of one of the other
things that I'm imagining that you're
doing especially you because like a lot
of what you're a lot of what your videos
are especially the ones where you're you
know that you're talking about where
you're you know making videos of you
listening in working out George Peterson
is on some level you're you're you're
showing people you're showing yourself
grapple with ideas and on some level
they're listening and getting the ideas
with you but you're also showing how to
grapple with an idea and how to come and
see in which is really I just want to
acknowledge I want to acknowledge what I
think Christopher actually acknowledged
before as well which is your your
willingness to go into these topics and
being a pasture right and being deeply
Christian with a open-mindedness right
to explore right that to me is a it's an
opening into that world right that I
think is I think is unfortunately rare
but I think you're you're demonstrating
and embodying a possibility that that
that that kind of that way of that way
where you're not only not threatened by
ideas right but but that there's there's
a way in which the more idea is that you
open to a more novelty that you bring in
it seems like creates a deeper ground in
yourself the more a more of a sense of
solidity or security that like opens to
more novelty and there seems to be that
part of the energy in the feel of your
channel is part of what's being
displayed is this that autopoietic
process right of mutuality that is it
doesn't seem to be threatening you at
all it seems to be deepening
deepening you so I think you're like a
really fine example I appreciate that a
lot
well I love what you said about the
presuppositions and I hadn't really
thought about it that way before but
you're right and one of the things that
sort of it should bother me more than it
does probably but it really doesn't is
that I really I really the the breadth
of people that I talk to on this Chando
channel really unnerve some other people
and I always find that unnerving
fascinating because it's like no no but
but you're right because when you do
listen to someone and if you are
actually listening you do step up upon
their presuppositions and inhabit that
and there is a fear that because you're
right
our presuppositions are what locate us
in this world yeah and and those
presuppositions are again as we began
this conversation these are inherited
frankly before we even start our own
autobiography they're inherited in our
context and our parents and they might
be that the faith that we inherit Roman
Catholicism or Dutch Reformed or
whatever might be two three generations
old but it's built in very deeply and
very young yeah and so it's a it's a
it's rightly a a significant and and
potentially hazardous thing to step upon
someone else's presupposition and listen
from there yeah but I think you're also
right that in many ways that's the only
way to connect with each other
yeah and that the terror of course is
that we will we will lose ourselves
right that we will that we will live it
with the the narrative thread that we
are will break yet and will and we'll
find ourselves lost so well thank you
that's a very that's a very big
compliment and I I
in many ways I have to credit my father
for this because I watched my father do
it I don't know if he did it consciously
but that that was that was who my father
was I one person who one person who knew
my father fairly well said you know your
father could get along with Hitler and
that's like like not that that lot not
that my father my father was anything
but a bigot if you understand the church
he mastered and the people he helped and
all of that but he he he had a
tremendous capacity for non-judgmental
engagement that didn't turn I see some
people with their non dead judgmentalism
they don't have a core but my father
both had a core running and knew how to
engage without judging right and and
that of course is in many ways what it
takes to do a gap a huh what what would
you say was the difference that made
that difference of that he was able to
like open non-judgmentally to people but
in a way that in a way that he still had
a core I would imagine it even like it
exemplified his core right you know I I
think you know there's a lot of talk and
then maybe John and I were gonna talk
Friday maybe we'll talk about this
we never know we're gonna talk about for
a talk usually but you know there's all
this talk right now about you know the
prob the the problematic aspect of
propositional truth and obviously
propositional truth alone as a part of
the other three P's the participatory
the perspectival and the and the
procedural one of you know I think part
of it had to very much do with with the
Dutch Calvinism of our tradition because
for for all of the all of the ways that
this Dutch Calvinism bothers us in terms
of its its seeming lack of openness what
it affords for those who have it deeply
have it deeply built into their psyche
is a radical openness because my you
know the the core of my destiny is not
finally dependent upon my performance
which means that I have been given
something that I cannot lose and and and
that isn't to be used as as license but
rather is a platform for agape because
if I have something that I cannot lose
why don't I pour out that which I have
for those who need huh yeah and my
father lived that yeah and so I you know
I didn't know what I was picking up from
him but when people say things to me
about me I think I probably got it from
him because he lived that yeah totally
so and you and I would imagine that
there's like you know one of the things
that is is as I don't hear a lot out a
lot of anymore is the notion of like
mentorship and our apprenticeship and
and I've noticed this in my class
actually I've noticed this in working
with families one of the things that I
do is I'll go into a family and I'll
I'll work with them as I made like
basically move in for a week or two and
I'll just and I have a guy Evan knack
for losing the guest in the house feel
[Laughter]
people like let down in fact they'll be
upset if you leave or are you leaving
here it's so interesting cuz all of
because what'll happen is the dynamical
happen right the reason why
they have me there right and then I'll
be in the corner right sipping my coffee
and there forget I'm there and you know
they're right before the dynamic like
locks and loads they'll be like buzz
right I can't them get you know real
like you can feel the dynamic lift and
then the real tragedy is revealed which
is you have these people that are
designed to love each other have no idea
each other are begin to have a
conversation yeah it's kind of notion of
like with a lot of them one in
particular they were so isolated from
each other that I couldn't I there is no
place that I could get I could catch
them because one of the magics of
working with families like this is like
it doesn't have that right I'm just me
and I show up right and it's kind of
embed myself in there yeah and then
usually usually most of like the intense
activity is like in the doorway like in
the car we're out there for three hours
because then these transition points
there is where all the all the stuff the
conversations that haven't been had
right happen but with one family they
were so isolated from each other that I
worked out something with the father
whereas it's like okay let's um let's
unplug the back of the house and just
say that the power went out which forced
everyone to sleep in the living room and
it in and so we all just weld in the
living room and it forced everyone to
like to have to interact with you to
participate in that way yeah right and
one of the big things that was lacking
is that everyone was so distant that
it's the sons didn't have the all of
them walking along with their dad mmm
coordinated activity of a tuning of like
working with wood together of like doing
a job together this way in which were
you're not it's you don't even you're
not even cocked like necessarily
consciously talking to each other but
you're both in a context in which just
the way that your dad Orient's right
in some way gets into your body and your
internal and in that the debt in some
way that deep that deep sense of
atonement with each other their a
participation is is I think a big one of
the magics of these of these
conversations is on one level there's
what we're talking about right but on
one level the topic of what we're
talking about you know almost could be
anything sometimes because there's
another thing that is transparent to us
right or opaque not necessarily like
front and center is that all of the
coordinated activities that's so rich
that I think is kind of makes makes us
mutually transform in some way i I agree
a hundred percent just look at a
marriage how many time how much times
people spend together not talking you're
about do it you know but there boy there
I got a run but you and I could talk all
day
absolutely I have no question about that
you and I could talk all day long
absolutely well we will talk again this
is and maybe next time I'm over in the
Bay Area I'll shoot you a text or
something and just let you know and if
you're free or something right we can
although people people will be upset
because we had conversation and we
didn't record it for them to listen but
well thank you so much guy I really I
really wish I didn't have to run so good
meeting you my friend so good meeting
you okay thank you